{
  "reference_number": "979",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "At risk of being unpopular, leaving out methane because our farming lobby dominates all others seems a bit weak. We need to look at\n ourselves - especially ruminants which are particularly inefficient at converting resource into protein. That will be the hardest issue to\n\n face in NZ given the size of the sector. Food production will always have an impact on our environment, but with all the science and\n technology we have amassed our consumption norms and habits have remained amazingly constant through the centuries."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Rather than just taxing and restraining as has been suggested in the past - e.g. oil exploration ban, there should be a pathway\ndemonstrated for creating new industries that are going to help the transition to lower resource use. Nobody is going to support a\n\nprogram that makes them poorer, there has to be a credible alternative for genuine buy-in. Create vehicles to support industries that\ndrastically improve our resource utilization efficiency. An example like govt has partnered to create the Food Innovation network helps\n\nthe private entrepreneurs to get off the ground, by providing infrastructure to succeed - professional, but they are not there to dole\nout money (or lose it). This has facilitated my own company's transition past the initial hurdle of finding a sympathetic commercial\n\nkitchen environment to create products and develop processes. We were assisted early with an incredible generosity (this could well\nhave changed since the demand for the facility has increased) but toward the end told to leave as we were too big, and rightly so."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes there needs to be expertise, but there also needs representation from different generations - someone with 50 years to live\nversus one with 20 years to live will quite possibly have different views on the relevance of climate change. That being said, expertise\n\nis important, but also partially people who have proven good decision making ability (does not need to be related to environment\nsector). Every person involved should have a proven common interest to protect our environment, and a long term view."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "One of the reasons RBNZ [was] for a long time held up as a global central bank leader, despite our tiny country, was because there\nwas one simple goal. Keep inflation between 0 and 2 %. By complicating what is already difficult task, we risk missing achieving the\n\ngoal all together. Potentially revenues gained from the process could be partially funneled towards remediation/adaption to climate\nchange. Although I prefer supporting a market innovator / entrepreneur to solve the problem. I see the governments role being one\nof facilitation, and they should not stand in the way of innovation (or try to do it themselves)."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
